here's some excerpts from man Jamuna kya
will try and include the PDF file from
which I'm reading as well maybe in a
link cluster and so the this first bit
is from much money come fifty two here
householder quite secluded from central
pleasures secluded from unwholesome
states a big who enters upon and abides
in the first jhana which is accompanied
by applied and sustained thought that
the translation with rapture and
pleasure born of seclusion he considers
this and understands it thus the first
John is conditioned and volitionally
produced so as it says here he considers
this and understands it thus not before
or after his Jannah but while he dwells
in that jhana with a pleasure born of
seclusion so this should dispel any
notion that some people might have it in
jhana you're thinking stops and you're
you're absorbed in some sort of
experience it's a it's a it's a clarity
of vision unshakeable mindfulness and
pleasure born of seclusion from the
unwholesome States sense of safety
that's the that's the pleasure there so
there is a there is a proper thinking in
it as in proper it's not rooted in greed
aversion and delusion it's not affected
by by central domain by the domain of
ill-will so once the minds establish that he
so once the minds establish that he
considers and understands with us the
first John is conditioned and
intentionally volitionally produced but
whatever his conditioning intentionally
produced is a reason on its own it's
subject to cessation it's impermanent so
he recognizes that even such a lofty
state such as the first jhana in this
case the state that it's beyond
everything unwholesome that it's utterly
wholesome there is nothing nothing
rooted in greed aversion delusion
in it and he recognizes the espera the
state is even this state is determined
by the intention to develop the state it
sees its determined by his efforts is
determined by his understanding is
determined by the clarity of his
mindfulness when those things cease when
his existence ceases in that manner that
this jhana
as long as it is cannot remain standing
so the reason why the Buddha emphasizes
this very often in very soon as it's
because obviously there is no clarity of
discernment when one is still rooted in
unwholesome but when one is rooted in
wholesome such as in the case of first
jhana he one turns his mind to the
nature of the reason phenomena at a time
he'll see that it still shares the same
nature as as other things even when the
mind is not in jhana things such as
cannot beyond a reason on its own it's
impermanent oppresses you so the the the
the the characteristics of of the
determinations and the reason why it's
always over said on the basis of
wholesome is just in case there are any
any any tendencies any other sort of
subtler notions that one might not have
considered they will be considered on
the basis of wholesome in other words it
will add like a it will work like a
blanket inside so to speak if one if
under understands that the nature of
impermanence the nature of suffering
that is subjected to its cessation on
its own terms if one understands that on
the basis of first jhana means nothing
else inferior to that can remain
unaffected by that understanding and and
that's what it says if we go further he
says if he studies his mind in that in
that discernment in that understanding
not in that mystical experience but in a
clarity of understanding that this is
impermanent he attains the destruction
of the taints but if he doesn't attain
the destruction of the taints and still
has some desire for the Dhamma
the lights in the Dhamma then with the
destruction the five lower fetters he
becomes one do to reappear spontaneously
in the pure bolts and their attained
finally bound without ever returning
from that world so he becomes a Nogami
this is one thing proclaimed by the
Blessed One who knows and sees
accomplished and fully enlightened
wherein if a baker buys diligent art and
resolute his unliberated mind comes to
be liberated his undestroyed things come
to be destroyed and he attains the
supreme security from bondage that he
had not attained before so this is the
the basis of first jhana to be used for
a direct insight into the into the
nature of things then further in the in
the same suta mm-hmm
it says says what island is the path the
way to the abandoning with the five
lower lower fetters here with the
seclusion from the acquisitions with the
abandoning of the unwholesome states
with a with the calming of bodily
inertia quite secluded from sensual
pleasures it's included from unwholesome
states a big who enters upon and abides
in the first jhana which is a compa
accompanied by thinking and pondering
with rapture and born of seclusion
adaption pleasure bone exclusion and
then there monk discerned whatever
exists within that experience as a
material form feeling perception
determinations and consciousness he sees
those states as impermanent as suffering
as disease as a tumor as a Bob as a
calamity as an affliction as an alien as
disintegrating as a void as not self
while he's in that experience if he will
turn that will turn his mind away from
those states and if he directs it about
the deathless element thus this is the
peaceful this is the sublime the
stilling of all determinations the
delinquency of all attachments the
destruction of craving dispassion
cessation Nibbana he studying that he
attains the destruction attains and then
goes on saying the same for as for the
previous passage so it's it's either
discerning the nature of of the
determination as
even though even the wholesome states
they do result in a sense of safety from
and pleasure and rapture bone from that
seclusion from the unwholesome States if
one discerns the nature of them the
universal nature of the arisen phenomena
one will see that it still subjected the
same things of impermanence and
suffering as a result of that anything
inferior to it cannot remain unaffected
as you said before the second part the
second way is to look at the whatever
exists in terms of the material forms of
them to look at the things the phenomena
as in the way of aggregates whichever
would experience as a whole and it's
more general peripheral nature which is
the nature of aggregates to see it as as
unwanted to see it as as dangerous as it
says here as a disease as a tumor as a
bar as a calamity as an affliction and
he knows that by seeing it like that
again any inferior desired a team I have
two particular things that are
manifested through his senses cannot
remain unaffected why because he is
experiencing a thorough dis passion
toward the nature of the form the nature
of the feeling the nature of perception
determinations and consciousness not
just this particular form of that
particular feeling or this particular
perception and so on so that's why the
mind is properly developed in terms of
their peripheral awareness then you can
apply it on to that level of the nature
of things not not a particular
absorption with one or the other
particular concern but the fundamental
nature if things are apply there no
particular concern can affect you ok so
here's one from matchmaker 5 it says
here friend this person with the blemish
who does not know as it really
there is a blemish in me he would not
arouse interest and make effort to
dispel that blemish so he would die with
a defiant mind
greed 8 and delusion so one thing
probably can be mentioned here is that
it's not any random blemish it's not
like some some obvious thing that the
person is tolerating that he knows it's
bad because it says he would die with
the Fineman with greed aversion greed
hate and delusion those are the
blemishes so that that must be a
standard in a criteria that should not
be compromised in other words even if
somebody starts with with the practice
they can't say ok well you know I'm a
petitioner so thus of course I have
greed a version delusion but I'm still
practicing saying that removes the
responsibility for greed aversion
delusion and if there is a removal of
responsibility for it they cannot be
effort applied for its uprooting if
you're delaying it you're not going to
be dealing with it so of course it's not
going to happen overnight and nobody
says that you should think it will
happen overnight but that doesn't mean
that you should then in the meantime so
to speak ignore responsibility for it no
on the contrary so if it takes you 10
years to develop the right view well for
10 years you have to feel the weight of
responsibility for greed evil delusion
never turn away but if you actually take
responsibility for your own greed
aversion delusion in such manner if we
won't take you 10 years to see through
it the reason why people don't see
through greed aversion is because they
delayed because they don't take
responsibility because as this suitor
says he does not see there is a blemish
in me as in what he thinks blemish is
it's usually not or or it's like the
obvious blemish but not the blemish that
the Buddha talks about in other words
his criteria of blemish is not
sufficiently developed but if you regard
greed aversion delusion doesn't matter
what particular exemplification of those
underlying tendency is there all you
care is that greed aversion of delusion
is there that's the blemish that's
because that's the work there nothing
less than that then there is a second
type of person is the person with a
blemish who knows as it really is this
is the blemish there is a blemish in me
and because of that he can then dispel
that blemish he would died he would die
with a non defiled mind without greed
hate a delusion why because he
recognized the debts the threshold for a
blemish and he undone it so suppose a
bronze dish were bought from a shop or
Saurus smithy it would be would be
covered with dust and stains and the
owner would use it and have it cleaned
and would not put it away in a dusty
corner would the bronze dish then get
more defiled and stain later on yes
friend so two friend a person with the
blemish who knows is it really there is
a blemish me with arouse interest and
make the effort to dispel that blemish
so he would die with a non-default mine
without greed aversion delusion oh you
know this again magic I might have read
this before but anyway it's a good
passage junda the idea that one this is
the Buddha saying this the idea that one
who has himself sank into the mud can
pull out another who is sunk into the
mud that's impossible the idea that the
one who has not sunk into the month
could pull out another who is sunk in
the mud that's possible the idea that
the one who himself is untamed untrained
an extinguished contained training help
us think each other that's impossible
the idea the one who himself is tame
train extinguish contain train help
extinguish another that is possible okay
let's see this one is a bit longer my
dream my 13 let's see what it says
friends the recluse Gautam
described the full understanding of
sensual pleasures and we do so to the
recluse Gautama describes the full
understanding of matter as in Rupa and
we do so to the recluse Gautama
describes the full understanding of
feelings and we do so too
what then is the distinction here
friends what's the variance was the
difference between the recluse gotama's
teaching and in our teaching between his
instruction and ours and the Buddha says
bhikkhus Wanderers of other sects who
speak thus should be questioned in this
manner a friends what is the
gratification what is the danger and
what is the escape in the case of
sensual pleasures what is the
gratification what is the danger what is
the escape in the case of matter what is
the gratification what is the danger
what is the escape in the case of
feelings being questioned us wonders of
other sects will fail to account for the
matter and what is more they will get
into difficulties why is that because
that's not the province because I see no
one in the world with its God it's Mara
these Brahmins any generation with
requisites and brahmins with its
princesses and its people who would
satisfy the mind with a reply to these
questions except for data-target a-- or
his disciple or the one who has learned
it from them
so people might wanders away why is that
wise why not a sex can other teachings
can explain basically when the Buddha
says the gratification the danger and
the escape in case sensuality in case of
matter in case of feelings means full
understanding means full understanding
of the duration of the reason phenomena
of the central domain not the particular
sensuality particular sensual desire but
the sensual domain as in possibilities
of sensuality are already with it all
the domain of matter the nature of
matter what we said before the general
nature of feeling the general nature of
matter so what is the gratification what
is the danger what is the what is the
escape all that isn't the basis of the
presently let's take feeling for example
what is the gratification what is the
danger what is the escape in case of
feelings so these three aspects are all
on the basis of the enduring feeling
they are not three separate things
they're just three things to discern
within the presently enduring feeling or
the presently enduring matter or the
present enduring sensual pleasures so
the gratification of these things like
the gratification of feelings it's it's
the say let's put a like this
gratifications in the feelings is the
possibility and the actuality of the
pleasure you can derive from it as in
when it goes your way when it obeys you
when it doesn't oppress you when it
offers even more pleasure there is the
genuine gratification in feelings there
is a genuine gratification in matter as
well for that matter because when the
matter obeys you when obeys your sense
of control assume sense of control when
obeys your wealth intentionality when
fulfills your projected notions of ideas
and desires that is the gratification in
it so it's like an offer offer of
ownership that you get verified to an
extent hence you feel gratified to that extent
hence you feel gratified to that extent
but even the offer of ownership is on
the basis of that presently enduring
thing which already means it's
impermanent because you are not
responsible for its presence nor for its
endurance so these random random
feelings that arise whatever they are
neutral Pleasant unpleasant neutral they
arise on their own central domain
manifests on its own matter man if it
like you are not its creator you cannot
even conceive being the creator you only
enter perceiving what's given to you to
be perceived now when you think oh it's
given to me to be perceived you're
perceiving that as well that notion is
also within the notion of your
perception which means that's not that
from which the matter has been given to
you so any notion that matter has been
given to you is thus a wrong notion
because it requires you to step outside
of yourself and to see where the matter
comes from to you and that's
inconceivable because even that thought
is within that perception there was
given to you within that matter that was
given to you that's how you recognize
that there is no external that you can
think of without misconceiving it you've
fully enclosed within the five
aggregates as a whole so experience of
external it's internal so to speak the
table said if a monk remembers his
previous life four or five previous
lives or five hundred previous life all
he remembers is the five aggregates of
one among them because that's that's
experience the whole there is nothing
outside of it when you think outside of
it that's within the five aggregates and
it's not incidental that the utter bada
the self view corresponds to the
gratuitous notion of self master
controller independent of your
experience as a whole as in external to
it that's exactly what it's rooted but
anyway let's get the gratification means
that the degree that you can exercise
your will your control your ownership
failing to see that that even that
degree as a possibility is secondary to
that independ
the rising of that thing whatever that
thing is beat matter or feeling or
sensuality failing to see it you take
you for granted and taking for granted
did that kind of relative offer of
relative ownership means absolute
ownership for you because that's all you
took that's all you see and that is the
gratification that's the gratification in the five
that's the gratification in the five
aggregates that's why people remain
bound with their ignorance now because
there is a mystical secret hidden behind
a veil of illusion or something no
because of their own very ignorant
intentions and acts that they can't say
no to pretty much and then it says what
is the danger so you can recompose the
talk now and think about yourself based
on what we said about the classification
think about what is the danger then if
the gratification is the author of that
relevant relative ownership that that
ends up pretty much intoxicating people
what is the danger except that
intoxication what is the danger that's
on the same level as that offered offer
prospect of pleasure of gratification of
control of mastery of verification of
your own assumed sense of self what is
the danger that's simultaneously there
as a second aspect
the danger is exactly rooted in the same
thing where the gratification is rooted
in saluted in that independently a
reason on its own presently enduring
feeling that you are subjected to it see
if you're just looking along the barrel
of gratification all you're gonna see is
the prospects of your gratification
you're not seeing the nature of the
basis upon which that clarification has
arisen you're not seeing the nature of
the feeling in the case we are
discussing but if you if you don't take
gratification for granted you just see
it as a prospect as a possibility but
you don't see it as you're right and you
certainly not careless in regard to it
then you see that gratification that has
arisen on the on the basis of the
presently enduring feeling on its own
that I'm subjected to that's why it's
dangerous because if I go with
gratification I can
not remain seeing the present enduring
feeling on its own I will have yeah
we're automatically it's not even a
matter of choice as in I will have to do
this you automatically by following
gratification its face value you
automatically appropriate that which is
independent of you which doesn't care
about you your feelings don't care about
you're invisible to your own feelings
you don't exist for them pretty much you
don't exist for the five aggregates you
exist only because you keep assuming
your own existence as the master
controller of them so if you don't
follow gratification its face value then
you don't automatically assume yourself
to be the owner of them so you recognize
that when you don't assume you recognize
how dangerous it is then that's the
danger there in that there isn't feeling
that offer of gratification offer of
confirmation of your ownership offer of
confirmation of your will intention
ality whatever that's the danger why
because the offer is rooted in the
present enduring thing that you have no
say in which means it's impermanent it
will come to cease and you can't even
like conceive it how that would not be
the case and that's the dangerous taking
such basis for granted is then dangerous
because it's going to affect you you
cannot remain indifferent if you have
taken the gratification of your feeling
for granted and then followed it when
that feeling changes you will be
affected and that's the danger and then
the the third aspect is understanding
the escape so what is the escape in the
case of feelings well this is this game
what we just described full
understanding of gratification and full
understanding of the danger means
developing the escape why because when
you genuinely recognize the danger of
taking the reason feeling is mind taking
it for granted you will turn away from
it you will not entertain that notion of
appropriation and gratification for not
even for a second longer
because is the most perilous thing and
thus you escape it so that's in Maj
America 13 mm for those who want to read
it but obviously we expanded on a bit
more okay goes magimai 15 that's
removing the blemishes we talked about
it okay well here is a an interesting
passage I think it's much in my 17 and
says here because a bigger bites
supported by a person when a body when a
body supported by person by a certain
person I suppose unestablished
mindfulness does not get established
unconcentrated mind an composed mind
does not get composed not destroy
desires do not get destroyed and the
unattainable end of the yoke is not
attained as for the full requisites of
life for the one gone forth robes food
dwellings requisites they are collected
without difficulty that big who should
thus reflect I abide supported by this
person and abiding thus my unestablished
mindfulness does not get established on
composed mind does not get composed on
destroy desire do not get destroyed on
attained noble end of yoke is not
attained as for the four requisites
robes food dwellings and medicine i
collected without difficulty that bhiku
shouldnt reflect further i did not go
forth as a homeless for the sake of
robes food dwellings or requisites when
I'm ill yet to me living supported by
this person not established mindfulness
does not get established not
concentrating mind is not concentrate
not destroyed as I do not get destroyed
and not at a noble end of York is not
attained because they're big who should
leave that person without informing them
so that he may not follow this this
refers to the I think this refers to the
teacher so this refers to a bhikkhu who
would live with under the mentorship I
suppose of a senior monk but he's not
progressing so the monastery might be
well supplied by everything that he
might need in terms of the requisites
but then he should reflect that that's
not why he went forth and he should have
sleeve I'm just leave right away but leave
I'm just leave right away but leave
without telling that person so that they
can't follow him it means it means
really prioritizing and reminding
yourself why you got into those in the
first place because the life won't last
forever even if a person lives 50 years
more that's nothing it's gonna go very
quickly and without thinking about the
end game of as the Buddha said himself
not attained a noble end well one is
one's gonna pay the price it probably
wasn't ready to bargain for because the
fact that the person was able first to
come across the was teaching secondly
able to lead the hearts of life and and
actually ordained that's already quite a
quite quite of like fortunate said the
circumstances in a way and of course
nobody's denying responsibility of
people who do that they are responsible
for their own going forward and
everything so they will take the credit
for it but all of that in itself will be
a wasted opportunity if a person does
not attain the noble end if they get
satisfied with just being a monk or or
living in a suitable environment they
need to then reflect further and
genuinely see whether the mindfulness
gets increased the composure the right
view gets developed if not well there is
no time to waste
that's pretty much
what this passage is saying let's see
where this one takes us magimai 11 and
says it was there these two views the
view of being in the view of non-being
the word for being is power the Pali
word any settings in Brahmins who adhere to
any settings in Brahmins who adhere to
the view of being were overpowered by
the view of being who hang on to the
view being there opposed to the Vietnam
being any other settings and brahmins
who are here to the view of non-being
who are overpowered by the view of
non-being who hang on to the Vietnam
being there opposed by the they're
opposed to the view being any setting in
Brahman who do not understand as they
actually are the origin setting down the
gratification the danger and the escape
in the case of these two views this is
what what we talked about just now and
if they don't understand those views
fully the origin setting down the
gratification the danger in the escape
they are affected by last anger delusion
assumption oppa Donna they are ignorant
they give in to favoring and imposing
they delight in and enjoy in
proliferation they are not free from
birth aging that sort of lamentation
pain grief and despair they're not free
from suffering as say any ascetic in
Brahman who does understand his the
actually are the origin setting down the
gratification danger and escape in the
case of these two views they are without
lust and the delusion holding there why
is not given to favoring and opposing
they do not delight in and enjoy
proliferation they are freed from birth
aging their sorrow lamentation pain
grief and despair tear free from
suffering I say
says mmm well it's not much to add here
unless we begin a whole new long
discussion about what being is and what
non-being is but practically even
passage that is presence we at least try
to understand no this may saw a system
like generic philosophy or something
because it isn't being and non-being
again in the most fundamental the most
general peripheral sense it's pretty
much either/or as in it's it's a it's a
if you push things peripherally you're
gonna say they're there or they're not
there either way the being is there the
denying of the being then you have the
non being but the fact that non being
you can designate you can have a view
rooted in it means even that is a thing
so just a negative denial of the being
and when the bullet talks that is about
bhava and we Baba it refers to the
absolutely fundamental most general
underlying view of a person and if if if
a person himself pushes and and tries to
discern his own views as far as he can
he'll see that he's gonna be rooted in
either fundamentally saying yes to his
existence or saying no to his existence
or more particularly Volz he might
sometimes say yes something say no but
fundamentally he's gonna have a view of
yes towards it or no towards it and that
that's what this means like the the
annihilation is and eternalists
as we will call again it wasn't just
like a slur that he developed to dismiss
out the philosophies of know it like if
you press those wrong views they're
gonna fall into these two categories on
the most fundamental general level the
ones they say yes yes and the one to say
the ones to say no and we said for as
long as that's the case then there is
lust anger
delusion and assumption are there if one
understands that that's how one develops
the middle way and that's how one is
free from lasting a delusion and
assumption free from ignorance it's on a
practical basis a person can reflect
just for asking asking certain questions
to oneself pretty much seeing what the
notion is what kind of attitude is
present there for example when you think
about death the inevitable that they
will have to happen that nobody wants to
think about to what degree is my sense
of self effected now most people if you
would just pick someone and see they
said well everybody dies that's it and
you realize they don't really allow the
notion of death to affect the sense of
self because it's way too terrifying
which means they fully they're fully
kind of encapsulated themselves you know
you know you know this protective view
of my being will be unaffected hence
there's on a fundamental level they
refused to say the infuse to even allow
possibility of no towards their own
being it's always a yes and even when
they face death externally witness it
they make they make sure it doesn't
apply to them through the view they've
used protect them from hope from having
it applied to themselves until of course
it's too late you can't you can hide
from it forever
death will come and if it hasn't been
faced while you were alive then it's too
late to deal with it
non-being would be the opposite will be
the denial of the being which again
fundamentally is a form of being in
itself that's why it's equally binding
as a wrong view is just through denying
it you assume the what's left after the
denial it's permanent is gonna last forever and
it's permanent is gonna last forever and
that's what you adhere to
hence if somebody says well see through
denying it you're still within the
nature of being they will get angry and
upset that's you see they would oppose
those views they would oppose the views
of being not of a particular being this
and that but the fundamental like say
like for example saying quite a common
view that we are nothing but they're
just a bunch of molecules hormones and
organs operating and just just the
basically physical matter when the body
breaks apart that's it that's nothing
nothing left nothing moves nothing comes
that's it that's the end of it
so it's a form of just denying the
validity of the being of your experience
as a whole just dismissing it through
scientific terms and scientific
observations and attributing your own
responsibility and properties just to
the molecules and hormones and chemicals
and whatnot but if somebody says we'll
see even that denial that you are
engaging in and and then you will be
doing so because through dismissing it
you think you're safe from that which is
subjected to death that's the
implication of it hence if you were to
point out that the notion in regard to
the dismissal of the being the notion
the kind of it is a background of it
well that is within the being because in
order to deny something that thing needs
to be present there and they have no say
in it in other words whether you affirm
the being or deny being that is
secondary to the presently arisen bhava
and whether you affirm the being or deny
being you just end up finding yourself
more to the assumption of the validity
of that being in the first place which
means you end up burning yourself even
more to that which is subjected to death
and destruction that's what we said when
people don't know the escape from being
then the revolving on the being
affirming denying if I mean either
affirming no denying they end up being
bound with a being he said it's like a
dog chained to a post tries to escape
the post ends up just running around the
post ends up just running around the
post and tying himself tighter and
tighter and tighter so that's that